בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. We are in the middle of a
long אגדתא, Agadata, which sort of started by a whole discussion about
the crossing of the ירדן Yarden at the time of יהושע, Yehoshua,
but it's also digressing to other related topics and now we're in
the middle of a whole story about the מרגלים. Meraglim. And most
recently we mentioned the fact that it uses the singular about when
it spoke to the מרגלים Meraglim arriving in חברון: Chevron: ויעלו בנגב
ויבא עד
חברון. Vaya'alu vanegev vayavo ad Chevron. And
the גמרא Gemara has it that only כלב Kalev went to חברון
Chevron to pray for protection from the אבות, Avot, ביקשו עלי רחמים.
bikshu alai rachamim. And רש"י Rashi points out nicely that that's the,
that that's the gives sort of the nice closure or parallel to
the fact that in the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, it's כלב Kalev
who gets חברון. Chevron. So that's the הארץ אשר דרך בה. Ha'aretz
asher darach bah. So there, it's a nice way of sort of
connecting those loose ends. Interesting little תוספות Tosafot here about אבותיי ביקשו
עלי רחמים. Avosai bikshu alai rachamim. אם תאמר והאמר פרק מי שמתו
דמייתי לא ידעי מידי, Im tomar veha'amar perek mishemeto demaisi lo yadin
midi, that the dead don't know anything. So why, how could you
be praying that the אבות Avot pray for you? They don't know
anything, they're in the other world. ומסקינן מסקנא ואפילו אבות העולם, Umaskin
maskana va'afilu avos ha'olam, even the אברהם, יצחק, ויעקב Avraham, Yitzchak, ve'Yaakov
are not aware about what goes on in this world. יש לומר
דעל ידי תפילה שזה מתפלל מודיעין להם שכך נתפלל. Yesh lomar de'al
yedei tefillah shezeh mitpallel modi'in lahem shekach nitpallel. Okay, that they don't
know directly, but they get like a little, they get informed. You
should be aware that it's been prayed down there in the lower
spheres, there's been prayers for you to make the following prayers. You
know, it's been prayed that you should pray on behalf of them.
So they don't directly hear the prayers, but they get like their
weekly summary of events that heard.
Their Monday morning update?
Monday morning update, exactly.
והאמר בפרק שני דתענית, Ve'amar b'perek sheni de-Taanis, למה יוצאין לבית הקברות
כדי שיבקשו עליהם מתים רחמים? lama yotzin leveit hakevarot kedei sheyivakshu aleihem
meitim rachamim? It has that same idea about going out to the
cemeteries that the מתים meitim should pray. ובכן בפרק דחסידים בעובדא דרבי
מנא דאשתטח אמערתא דאבוה Uv'chein b'perek de-Chasidim b'uvda de-Rabbi Mana de-ishtatach amarta
d'avuha during bowing,
prostrating on the graveside of his father. So, again, this is obviously
a practice specifically that's encoded in מנהג minhag and in about during
the עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseres Yemei Teshuva. And it's one that there's
some debate about, not because about the question that תוספות Tosafot raises
about will it do any good, do the מתים meitim know what
you're praying for, but because here the point is that you pray
for them to pray for you. So it's more like you request
of them to make the prayer on your
behalf. And if you take a look, one of them was just
going to the בית הקברות beit hakevarot somehow stirs up their prayers
on your behalf. And the concern is that does it always remain
that way? You know, when people go
there, it's very likely that they actually direct their prayers to the
מתים, meitim, not just saying please pray to God on my behalf
and
so on. So then it really becomes a תפילה tefillah to some
being other than God, which obviously
is, can, רמב"ם Rambam would be horrified at that and
even in a way of like of doing it as a form
of an intermediary. But when it stops being an intermediary and when
it starts being the thing that is being prayed to, sometimes that
line gets quite blurred. So there are people that are very against
this practice. Even the role of
intermediary, on the one hand, we have a שליח ציבור shaliach tzibbur
who sort of represents
us, and there was mentioned the whole מכניסי רחמים, Machnisei Rachamim, which
is angels that you're sort of asking to be מכניס machnis your
רחמים. rachamim. But at what stage
do intermediaries
become, it's a little bit different, the שליח ציבור. shaliach tzibbur. First
of all, it's this-worldly, it's a representative, it's not so much of
an intermediary.
And it's a little different, we're sort of seen as praying together
with the שליח ציבור, shaliach tzibbur, not that he's sort of doing
it
on our behalf. So the problem about in general how comfortable somebody
feels about the idea of intermediary and number two about specifically about
the blurring of the line, that's a real issue. On the other
hand, like we have even in the תורה, Torah, משה Moshe prays
on behalf of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael etc. And at a time
when people could control their world a lot less than they can
control their world nowadays, and there was a lot more
anxiety, you want to use
any tools at your disposal and to help have your prayers heard
by God. So it does raise a lot of interesting questions. Yes.
Charlie, as you might guess from my background, this is very upsetting
because many Christian groups never pray to God. They only pray to...
Aha. But do they say, "Please X, bring my prayers to God,"
or do they pray directly to...
They pray, many Christians pray directly to an intermediate, a deceased
saint.
Aha. Yeah. And they pray that the saint should answer their prayers.
Saint so-and-so, please help me. Saint so-and-so... so they have different saints
in charge of different things. They'll say, "Please Saint such-and-such, help me
with this problem."
Right. So that becomes the actual sort of thing that is being
prayed to.
Not that they don't believe in God, it's just they don't pray
to God.
Right. Which is interesting. You know, I mean look, it gets to
the whole challenge about a non-physical God and why for Christianity, having
God take a human form or whatever just makes God something much
more relatable. So it's not surprising that you also can pray therefore
to dead saints, which are people, used to walk on this earth
and are
people, were people, and therefore something that more can be related, closer
to you and relatable. So it's understandable, yeah.
Isn't that close to the concept of זכות אבות? Zechut Avot?
זכות אבות Zechut Avot is not how you're directing your prayers. That's
that you merit from the זכות zechut that's being carried down through
the generations.
But you stand before God and you say, "May I have the
merit of..."
Yeah, that's very different. I mean it relies on...
You understand the difference? Yeah. It's not so different that it's like
way off the continuum. It's like right the next door...
No, I don't think so. I don't think so. One requires a
certain just metaphysics about how God does his accounting, and the other
is actually the question about the nature of worship. I think that
they're very different.
Okay, so anyway, so now we pick up...
okay, so we had this whole discussion about חברון שבע שנים נבנתה.
Hevron sheva shanim nivneta. We were discussing a little bit about חברון.
Hevron. And the גמרא Gemara says like this:
וישבו. Vayashuvu. Is that where we're up to, וישבו? Vayashuvu? Yes. Last
line on ל״ד עמוד ב׳. Lamed Dalet Amud Bet. וישובו מתור הארץ
מקץ ארבעים יום, Vayashuvu mitur ha'aretz miketz arba'im yom, and they returned
from scouting out the land.
וילכו ויבאו. Vayelchu vayavo'u. So why does it say they went and
they came? So what, I mean, they're seeing the גמרא's Gemara making
some parallel about the פסוק pasuk that talks about them going and
the פסוק pasuk that talks about them coming.
אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי מקיש הליכה לביאה. Amar
Rabi Yochanan mishum Rabi Shimon ben Yochai, makish halicha livi'ah.
Meaning the whole עצה רעה etza ra'ah thing. Yeah, exactly.
מה ביאה בעצה רעה, Ma bi'ah be'etza ra'ah, the same way when
they returned they were in, they were in cahoots and they had
a bad, like they
you know... Bad report. No, no, no. עצה Etza means that they
had an עצה. etza. They, you know, they had a... They themselves
had a collusion. Right. אף הליכה בעצה רעה. Af halicha be'etza ra'ah.
Even when they left, they had already left with a similar type
of a plan, of an evil plan. Okay. ויספרו לו ויאמרו באנו
אל הארץ אשר שלחתנו וגם זבת חלב ודבש היא וזה פריה. Vayisapru
lo vayomeru banu el ha'aretz asher shelachtanu vegam zavat chalav udevash hi
veze pirya. Is that right? וזה פריה. Veze pirya. Okay. So yes,
it's a land flowing with milk and honey, here's the fruit. אפס
כי עז העם. Efes ki az ha'am. Only little bit of a
problem is that they're too strong for us. So וכתיב אפס כי
עז העם. Uchtiv efes ki az ha'am. So that's a pretty radical
shift from saying it's beautiful and flowing with milk and honey and
then they say, "But here's the problem." אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי
מאיר כל לשון הרע שאין בו דבר אמת בתחילתו אין מתקיים בסופו.
Amar Rabi Yochanan mishum Rabi Meir, kol lashon hara she'ein bo devar
emet bit'chilato ein mitkayem besofo. If any לשון הרע lashon hara that
you do not have some truth to it... right? A good liar
knows how to make his lies very close to the actual truth,
because then it just makes
it much more believable and it resonates with people. So if you
don't have... so any לשון הרע lashon hara that you don't have
something true in it in the beginning, it will not survive. People
won't... it won't have any lasting effect. But if it's close to
the truth, then people believe it. Interesting here, you know, the חפץ
חיים Chafetz Chaim is very מקפיד makpid to distinguish between לשון הרע
lashon hara and מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra. That לשון הרע
lashon hara is true gossip and מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra
is slander, it's false gossip. But here the גמרא Gemara is not
doing it. לשון הרע Lashon hara also has a much more generic
meaning, which just means the evil speech, harmful speech, and it could
be of many sorts. But anyway, but here clearly we're talking about
slander. Okay. ויחס כלב את העם אל משה, Vayahas Kalev et ha'am
el Moshe, and Caleb silenced the people to Moses. So אמר רבא
שהסיתם בדברים. Amar Rava she'hisitam bidvarim. ויהס Vayahas to silence, sort of
has good onomatopoeia. ויהס, Vayahas, okay. So he hushed... might be a
close
one. Okay, anyway, שהסיתם, she'hisitam, but it's using it differently. He seduced
them with words or he incited them, incited them. But it's sort
of a combination. פתח יהושע דקא משתעי. Patach Yehoshua deka mishta'ei. So
Joshua started to try to talk, because the whole question is why
is it Caleb, why not Joshua? No, no, no, Joshua tried to
quiet the people to stand up to them. Okay. אמרו ליה, Amru
lei, but they said to him, דין ראש קטיעא ימלל? Dein rosh
keti'ah yemallel? This, the head of the cut-off one should speak? So
what's ראש קטיעא? rosh keti'ah? So רש״י Rashi says it means that
יהושע Yehoshua didn't have children. So they said, "Yeah, he doesn't have
a stake in it, he's not going to inherit the land, so
therefore why should we listen to him?" to him, he's now he
doesn't have a stake, you know, he's
he's talking without a vested interest. So we don't believe him. So
the another interpretation, the הערוך ha'Aruch says that ראש קטיעה Rosh Ketia
is because his name started with a י, Yud, you know, משה
Moshe called הושע בן נון, Hoshea Bin Nun, יהושע. Yehoshua. So he's
got a tiny little letter at the beginning of his name. So
it was just like an insult. I mean, I don't know why
that was an insult. Maybe it means a י Yud is like
a cut-off letter? Yeah, exactly. A י Yud is a tiny little
cut-off letter. So this shrimp should talk, you know, whatever? It's just
a way of silencing him. But they saw that whatever they would
do, you know, כלב Calev saw that they'd find some way to
just be dismissive of him. So אמר, Amar, אם אשתעינא, Im ishta'ina,
if I try to talk, אמרי בי מילתא, amrei bi milta, they'll
say something about me, וחסמי לי, vachasmi li, they'll silence me, they'll
muzzle me. אמר להם, Amar lahem, so he said to them, so
how what am I going to do to get them on my
side? וכי זו בלבד עשה לנו בן עמרם? Vachi zo bilvad asa
lanu ben Amram? Do you think this is the only thing that
the son of Amram did to us? Notice he calls משה Moshe
בן עמרם Ben Amram as a way of being like dismissive and
right and degrading towards משה, Moshe, a degrading term, right? Do you
think this, this son of Amram, this is the only thing he
did to us? סברי, Savrei, בגנותיה קא משתעי, bigunutei ka mishta'ei, they
thought
he was going to say something bad about משה. Moshe. אשתקו, Ishtaku,
so they were silent, they wanted to hear it to feed their
flames. אמר להם, Amar lahem,
he said to them, הוציאנו ממצרים, hotzianu miMitzrayim, ובקע לנו את הים,
uvaka lanu et hayam, והאכילנו את המן. vehe'echilanu et haman.
So look at all the things he did to us! He did
all these miracles. אם יאמר עשו סולמות ועלו לרקיע, Im yomar asu
sulamot va'alu larakia, לא נשמע לו? lo nishma lo? Even if he
said to make ladders and to try to go up to heaven,
would we not listen? Like an אלונה בבבל, Aluna b'Bavel, right? I
understand. Do you think, עלינו נעלה! Alinu na'aleh! That's playing off עלה
נעלה. aleh na'aleh. Wherever he tells us to go, we'll go! Look
at everything he's done to us. It's always proven faithful in his
promises and able to do anything, even the
miraculous. Okay. It's almost the inverse of what the גמרא Gemara said
before about the לשון הרע lashon hara that starts with a דבר
אמת. dvar emet. So here was a דבר שקר dvar sheker to
get to a דבר אמת. dvar emet. Right. He was, he made
them believe that he was on their side as an... I know,
but it was a similar, it was a similar inverse parallel.
He says and not to praise him, you know, that speech...
Oh, that's a good example! Comes to bury Caesar, not to praise
him, right, right. Good example.
Excellent,
excellent tie-in, yeah. Okay,
alright. Don't get me started, I'll start quoting whole passages. Okay, and
it says like this. Okay, alright. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa,
דבר גדול... dvar gadol... Okay, where are we? והאנשים אשר עלו עמו
אמרו, Veha'anashim asher alu imo amru, לא נוכל לעלות,
lo
nuchal
la'alot, כי חזק הוא ממנו. ki chazak hu mimenu. He, the people
are greater than us. אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא, Amar Rabbi Chanina
bar Papa, דבר גדול דיברו מרגלים, dvar gadol dibru meraglim, that was
a huge thing that they said, not a good thing, a huge
terrible thing. באותה שעה, Be'ota sha'ah, כי חזק הוא ממנו, ki chazak
hu mimenu, greater than us, אל תקרי ממנו... al tikrei mimenu... now
רש"י Rashi says it's not really a different word here but it's
a way of understanding, of explaining. Do not understand this to mean
greater than us, אלא ממנו, ela mimenu, greater than Him. It's the
same word. But רש"י Rashi says, so רש"י Rashi takes out the
גירסא, girsa, changes the גירסא. girsa. But the point is, it's a
nice way of underscoring what ממנו mimenu means. It doesn't mean ממנו
mimenu us, it means greater than Him, greater than God. כביכול, Kivyachol,
as if they were saying, אפילו בעל הבית אינו יכול להוציא כליו
משם. afilu ba'al habayit eino yachol lehotzi kelav misham. Even the owner,
you know, can't take his vessels out of his own house. ארץ
כנען Eretz Canaan is like, you know, God's place. They're so strong,
even God can't sort of do anything there. Right. Yeah, exactly. So
I do want to say an interesting thing about
this ממנו. mimenu. There's a, you know, רמב"ם Rambam writes that one
of the... about the whole famous רמב"ם Rambam who says that one
of the י"ג עיקרים yud gimmel ikkarim is believing that God not...
you know, believing that God does not have a body. And that
somebody who believes that God has a body is, you know, אין
לו חלק לעולם הבא, ein lo chelek l'olam haba, and it doesn't
matter even if they came to it because of some, you know,
mistaken belief and they, you know, even if they... you know, they
should learn from people who know better, etc., etc. רמב"ם Rambam was
not... the phrase you might have heard the phrase, נעבך אפיקורוס nebach
apikorus is still an אפיקורוס. apikorus. You know, I don't care whether
it was his fault or not. Anyway, the רמב"ם Rambam wrote about
this extensively. It doesn't matter if you have such a corrupt belief
of God, אין לו חלק לעולם הבא. ein lo chelek l'olam haba.
So on that, now you have to realize that at that time
there were a lot of people that believed that God had some
form of some ethereal body. I mean, you take all of the
metaphors in the תורה Torah and you read them literally. We're right,
you know, exactly, you know. So we are, some people actually question,
you know, question... you know, we sort of see, you know, when
we read רמב"ם Rambam and his big fight against the anthropomorphisms, I
think we probably imagine, yeah, there were a few outliers that he
had to silence, but I think, you know, scholars have questioned like
maybe significant segments of the population. It's a question exactly how pervasive
it was also among scholars, among the common people. Anyway, so הראב"ד
the Ra'avad there on the רמב"ם Rambam writes, he says, how could
he say that? והגדולים ממנו אמרו שיש לו גוף. vehagedolim mimenu amru
sheyesh lo guf. People greater than he said that God has a
body. So how could he say אין לו חלק לעולם הבא? ein
lo chelek l'olam haba? So people have said, okay, הראב"ד, the Ra'avad,
you want to defend the people that said that and believed that...
How many people were there that you could put in that category
of greater than the רמב״ם? Rambam? So somebody suggested, I forget who
it was, might have been the חזון איש, Chazon Ish, so he
suggested that the way to read it is גדולים ממנו, Gedolim mimenu,
not greater than he, but it's the reverse of the ממנו, mimenu,
אל תקרי ממנו אלא ממנו. Al tikri mimenu ela mimenu. There were
great people from among us the Jewish people who believed that. Anyway,
I don't know if it's פשט, Pshat, but it was a good
say. Okay, who else? I don't know, but okay. There was one
of the בעלי תוספות Baalei Tosafot believed that God had a body.
So I forget who it was, but okay. Moving on. ארץ אוכלת
יושביה היא, Eretz ochelet yoshveha hi, okay, it's a land that eats
its inhabitants. דרש רבא, Darash Rava, אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, אני חשבתי לטובה, Ani chashavti letova, I yes, I arranged
that, but I was planning, I was doing it for their good,
והם חשבו לרעה, Vehem chashvu leraa, and they interpreted it for bad.
אני חשבתי לטובה, Ani chashavti letova, I planned the whole thing for
good. בכל היכא דמטו Bechol hecha dematu מית חשיבא דידהו, Meis chashiva
didehu, wherever they went, an important person from among them died, כי
היכי
דניטרדו,
Ki
heichi denitardu,
so wherever they went, the people would all be distracted, ולא לישאלו
אבתרייהו, Velo lishalu avtraiyehu, they wouldn't ask who are these strange people
traveling through the land.
ואיכא דאמרי, Ve'ika d'amri, and some say איוב נח נפשיה. Iyov nach
nafsheia. No, איוב Iyov died, ואטרידו כולי עלמא בהספידא, Vatridu kulei alma
behespeda, and everybody was busy with the הספידא Hespeda of איוב, Iyov,
which is an interesting parallel about them going up beforehand, you know,
with יעקב Yaakov and all of, we had אגדתא Agadata about that
and about how everybody was involved in the הספד Hesped of יעקב,
Yaakov, you know, that was almost like a precursor to their going
to the land, like a sort of מעשה אבות סימן לבנים, Maaseh
avot siman labanim, leaving מצרים Mitzrayim going to the land. So now
here everybody else is involved in a הספד Hesped of a great
person, and the one great non-Jewish person that we sort of know
of, you know, is איוב. Iyov. Of course, it's still interesting because
since איוב Iyov was such a righteous man and he was recognized
as great, it's sort of like, you know, you want to sort
of cast the כנענים Kenaanim as רשעים, Reshaim, right? You don't want
to sort of recognizing such a great person. So רש״י Rashi says
what making it איוב Iyov also does is it explains that סר
צלם מעליהם, Sar tzilam me'aleihem, their protection has been removed from them,
that איוב's Iyov זכות Zechut no longer is there to protect them.
And once he's dead, now, you know, of course, where was איוב
Iyov living? Was he, I mean, the פסוקים Psukim say he was
living in ארץ עוץ, Eretz Utz, which is not exactly ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael last I checked. So I don't know, anyway, yes. There
are other גמרות Gemarot that just savagely criticize איוב Iyov for not
praying to God, for not having proper belief. Right, but I guess
the thinking was it was the best they could do. So alright,
anyway, okay. Okay, הם חשבו לרעה, Hem chashvu leraa, ארץ אוכלת יושביה
היא, Eretz ochelet yoshveha hi, and they interpreted it all as evil,
oh my God, it's a land that consumes its inhabitants. ונהי בעינינו
כחגבים וכן היינו בעיניהם, Vanehi be'eineinu kachagavim vechen hayinu be'eineihem, and we
were in our own eyes like grasshoppers and so we were in
their eyes. אמר המשרשיא, Amar Hamasharshiya, מרגלים שקרי הוו, Meraglim shikrei havu,
they were liars. Like that's a חידוש, Chidush, I don't know, but
until now they haven't said anything that exactly was a lie, right?
I mean, ארץ אוכלת יושביה Eretz ochelet yoshveha is an interpretation, right?
Somehow, you know, it's all a question of how do you interpret
the facts. But here he's saying they were actually lying. Okay, so
שקרי הוו. Shikrei havu. בשלמא ונהי בעינינו כחגבים לחיי, Bishlama vanehi be'eineinu
kachagavim lachayei, we were in our own eyes like grasshoppers, okay, that
makes sense. אלא וכן היינו בעיניהם מנא ידעי, Ela vechen hayinu be'eineihem
mna yadei, how did you know what you looked like in their
eyes? והגמרא Vehagemara says ולא היא, Velo hi, no, that's not true,
you don't have to say they were liars. ולא היא כי הוו
מברי אבילי תותי ארזי, Velo hi ki havu mavrei aveilei tutei arzei,
so when they would, you know, sort of cater to the mourners
under the cedar trees, they would give the mourners these, you know,
meals, so that's הבראה, Havraah, okay, so they would because everybody was
dying, you know, they had all these deaths that were going on.
So תותי ארזי הוו מברי. Tutei arzei havu mavrei. וכי חזינהו, Vechi
chazinhu, and when בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael saw them coming to the
cedar trees, סלקי יתבי באילני, Salki yatvei be'ilanei, so they needed to
go hiding, so they went up and they climbed up into the
trees. שמעו דקאמרי, Sham'u deka'amri, and then they heard them saying, קחזינן
אינשי דדמו לקמצי באילני, Kachazinan inshei dedamu lekamzei be'ilanei, we see people
that look just like grasshoppers in the trees. So we knew what
we were in their eyes. Now, why do you think they introduced
the trees in this story?
Why didn't they just say they heard them saying? It's a, first
of all, it's a cell and if we talk about the... ah,
maybe, but היש בה
עץ אם אין.
Hayesh
ba etz im ayin.
I think it's a simpler answer. How did they get... they're so
tall, how do you hear what they're saying? You gotta get up
there.
So that's how they come at them in the trees.
Okay, okay. ותשא כל העדה ויתנו את קולם,
Vatissa kol ha'eda vayitnu
et
kolam, the whole people lifted up their voice, ויבכו העם בלילה ההוא,
Vayivku ha'am balayla hahu, and they cried on that night. אמר רבה
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabba amar Rabi Yochanan, אותו היום או אותו
הלילה ערב
תשעה באב היה.
Oto hayom o oto halayla
erev Tisha B'Av haya.
Okay, that was the night of תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, הם בכו בכיה של חנם, Hem
bachu bechiya shel chinam,
בלילה ההוא, Balayla hahu, there's some emphasis about
that night, that night is a momentous night, a night of significance.
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, הם בכו בכיה של
חנם, Hem bachu bechiya shel chinam, they cried for nothing, I'll give
them something to cry about, so אני אקבע להם בכייה לדורות, ani
ekba lahem bechiya l'dorot, I'll make it a night of crying for
future generations. And that was the first sort of, you know, the
first of the things that happened on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av was
the report of the spies. ויאמרו כל העדה לרגום אותם באבנים, Vayomru
kol ha-eidah lirgom otam ba-avanim, that's the verse Rabbi David you're talking
about, זכות אבות, zechut avot, here's the sort of carrying off, paying
back the sin over many generations. And all the congregation wanted to
stone them with stones. וכתיב וכבוד ה' נראה באהל מועד, U-chtiv u-chevod
Hashem nir'ah b'Ohel Moed, and then immediately to sort of interrupt, God's
presence, God's, the honor, the כבוד ה' kvod Hashem was appeared in
אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא מלמד שנטלו אבנים
וזרקו
כלפי מעלה,
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba melamed she-natlu avanim v'zarku
klapei
ma'ala, they sort of
like sort of similar to the previous statement of ממנו. mimenu. They
threw their stones at God because they're reading it לרגום אותם באבנים
וכבוד ה' lirgom otam ba-avanim u-chevod Hashem to stone them and the
honor of God. They were trying to even stone God. וימותו האנשים
מוציאי דיבת הארץ רעה במגפה,
Vayamutu ha-anashim
motzi'ei
dibat ha-aretz ra'ah ba-mageifah, and the people who, you know, spread the
evil report died in a plague, in an in an horrible plague.
So what's the רעה? ra'ah? Is it הארץ רעה ha-aretz ra'ah or
רעה במגפה? ra'ah ba-mageifah? Seems to be a little bit possibly how
the גמרא Gemara is reading it. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש שמתנו
מיתה משונה. Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish she-metu mitah meshunah. רש"י Rashi
says it's במגפה, ba-mageifah, the מגפה, mageifah, like some particularly horrible one.
Others say the word רעה ra'ah is being read in conjunction with
מגפה. mageifah. It was a very, it was a very unusual death.
אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא דרש רב שילא איש כפר תמרתא מלמד,
Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa darash Rav Shila ish Kefar Tamarta melamed,
so this is the דרשה drasha that this רב שילא Rav Shila
gave. It teaches you שנתשרבב לשונם, she-nishtarbev lishonam, their tongues sort of
rolled down, like stretched down, ונפל על טיבורם v'nafal al tiburam and
went to their belly buttons. והיו תולעים יוצאין מלשונם ונכנסות בטיבורם V'hayu
tola'im yotzin mi-lishonam v'nichnasot b'tiburam and the worms were came out of
their tongues to obviously, you know, emphasize that they spoke לשון הרע
lashon hara and they would go, you know, and how they misused
their speech and go into their belly buttons. ומטיבורם ונכנסות ללשונם U-mi-tiburam
v'nichnasot l'lishonam and they would do a cycle. They'd go from their
belly buttons to their, you know, to their to their tongue and
from their tongue to their belly buttons. ורב נחמן בר יצחק אמר
באסכרה מתו. V'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar ba-askara metu. No, they died
with אסכרה askara which is the croup. Like because obviously these are
a plague, you know, it's all about evil speech, so it's about
the tongue or the throat and that's where it attacks. The interesting
thing about the טיבור tibur seems to be because, you know, when
the גמרא Gemara in יומא Yoma discusses טיבור העולם. tibur ha-olam. Well,
טיבור tibur is the center, but also when the גמרא Gemara discusses
like how do you check if somebody's alive, do you check their,
you check, you know, do you check their breathing or do you
check עד טיבורו ad tiburo until the, until the what do you
call it, the belly button, that that also was like the center
of life was the, you know, was an understanding. So basically it's
like, you know, going into their essence and coming out of their
essence. Okay. וכיון שעלה האחרון שבישראל מן הירדן, V'keivan she-alah ha-acharon she-b'Yisrael
min ha-Yarden, now we're back to יהושע. Yehoshua. That was a little
digression to the מרגלים. meraglim. Back to יהושע. Yehoshua. They weren't going
in and out of their body were they? Yes, they were. What
do you mean? They were going inside their, yeah, they went from
their tongue into their body and then came back out again. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. It's like, you know about, you know about the water
cycle? This was the worm cycle. Okay. The worm cycle came after
the water cycle. Right, okay. וכיון שעלה האחרון שבישראל מן הירדן, V'keivan
she-alah ha-acharon she-b'Yisrael min ha-Yarden, now when the last one of Israel
left, now we're back to the rocks and the באר היטב. be'er
heiteiv. Okay. Same ברייתא braita still? Yeah, seems to be. When the
last of the, of the Israelites left the Jordan, חזרו מים למקומם,
chazru mayim limkomam, the water returned to its their place. שנאמר ויהי
בעלות הכהנים נשאי ארון ברית ה' מתוך הירדן, She-ne'emar vayhi ba-alot ha-kohanim
nosei aron brit Hashem mi-toch ha-Yarden, when the כהנים, kohanim, you know,
left, went out of the Jordan, נתקו כפות רגלי הכהנים, nitku kapot
raglei ha-kohanim, they, when they they detached the, the, you know, the
the soles of the feet of the כהנים—אל החרבה, or I'm sorry,
they they entered, they went to the dry land. So once their
soles hit dry land, וישובו מי הירדן למקומם v'yashuvu mei ha-Yarden limkomam
and the waters of the Jordan, so this is a quote of
a פסוק—went pasuk back to their place. וילכו כתמול שלשום Vayelchu ki-tmol
shilshom and they returned to their prior strength. על כל גדותיו Al
kol gedotav on all of its, you know, banks. Right, because the
earlier פסוקים psukim it actually interestingly wasn't quoted in the גמרא, Gemara,
but says that it was like after all of the snows had
melted and whatever, so it was like the Jordan was at its
strongest. נמצא—now, Nimtza but the גמרא Gemara reads this is, because if
you read the פסוקים psukim it actually would be quite interesting, because
when does the Jordan split? As soon as the כהנים kohanim enter
it, right? So if as soon as they enter it the Jordan
split, they're on which side of the Jordan? The east or the
west bank? I assume the... the east bank. Everybody passes, and then
it says, and then they stepped out of the Jordan. So they
stepped out, they're stepping back out on the east bank. Okay, so
they're on the wrong side. They needed to have walked across the
Jordan. Okay, so now you could say that that's what it means,
עלות alot that they went up after they had crossed it. But
anyway, but it's—but then it says נתקו כפות רגליהם אל החרבה, nitku
kapot ragleihem el ha-charavah, they're sort of reading it like their feet
just took one step back and they stepped on the dry land.
So the גמרא Gemara says as a result of that we got
a bit of a problem here. נמצא ארון ונושאיו וכהנים מצד אחד.
Nimtza aron v'nos'av v'kohanim mi-tzad echad. The ארון aron and the carriers
and the כהנים kohanim are all on the east side of the
Jordan. The And the Israel is on the west side of the
Jordan. So how did they get over? So it says נשא ארון
את נושאיו. Nassa Aron et nosav. Ah, the ארון Aron lifted them
up and carried them miraculously carried them over. So the ארון Aron
was נושא את נושאיו. nosei et nosav. It lifted those that were
carrying it. Really? It says that the לוחות Luchot also, the לוחות
Luchot carry themselves. Right, exactly. דכתיב, Dechtiv, ויהי כאשר תם כל העם
לעבור ויעבור ארון ה' והכהנים לפני העם. Vayehi ca'asher tam col ha'am
la'avor vaya'avor Aron Hashem vehacohanim lifnei ha'am. The ארון Aron first passed
without the כוהנים, Kohanim, meaning it's logically it's a strange פסוק. pasuk.
The כוהנים Kohanim and the ארון Aron passed. The ארון Aron didn't
pass by itself. It's the כוהנים Kohanim passed and they brought with
them the ארון. Aron. But no, the ארון Aron passed and it
was the ארון Aron that brought over the כוהנים Kohanim לפני העם.
lifnei ha'am. ועל דבר זה נענש עוזא, Ve'al davar zeh ne'enash Uza,
not appreciating the power of the ארון, Aron, this is what עוזא
Uza was punished for. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, as the פסוק pasuk says, ויבואו
עד גורן כידון, Vayavo'u ad goren kidon, they came to the threshing
floor of כידון. Kidon. וישלח עוזא ידו לאחוז את הארון, Vayishlach Uza
yado le'echoz et ha'aron, this is when they were moving the ארון
Aron from, you know, trying to bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim by
King David. And they were passing through this גורן כידון, goren kidon,
and he thought it looked like, you know, that the wagon that
it was on was slipping and it was כי שמטו הבקר, ki
shamtu habakar, that the cattle slipped and he tried to catch the
ארון, Aron, לאחוז את הארון, le'echoz et ha'aron, and then he was
smitten right there, you know, at, you know, on the spot. So
אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so God
said to him: עוזא, Uza, עוזא, Uza, נושאיו נשא, nosav nasa, the
ארון Aron lifted up those who lifted it. עצמו לא כל שכן,
Atzmo lo col sheken, it can take care of itself, it doesn't
need you. ויחר אף ה' בעוזא ויכהו שם על השל. Vayichar af
Hashem be'Uza vayakehu sham al hashal. So you didn't appreciate the power
of the ארון. Aron. ויחר אף ה' בעוזא ויכהו שם על השל.
Vayichar af Hashem be'Uza vayakehu sham al hashal. And God's anger was
kindled against עוזא Uza and he smote him there on the error.
So it's interesting he calls it an error, השל, hashal, right, it's
not מזיד, meizid, I mean he was trying to do something good,
but nevertheless it's sort of like one of these הקדוש ברוך הוא
מדקדק עם הצדיקים Hakadosh Baruch Hu medakdek im hatzadikim type of a
thing, or this was something you needed to understand. I mean, you
know, the other point about it also is that, you know, it's
sort of also like, you know, the, what do you call them,
נדב ואביהוא Nadav ve'Avihu and so on. Somebody has likened it to
sort of like, you know, the power of the presence of God
like sort of like a power plant, right? You know, which is
like you got all those things, you know, you know, all those
skull and bones around a power plant, right? You know, high voltage,
you know, so it's a danger etc. So you get too close
unprotected, right, it gives light and it gives power to the whole
world, but you get too close unprotected, you do the wrong thing
and also the consequences are very severe. Yes, but when בני ישראל
Bnei Yisrael crossed the ירדן, Yarden, the כוהנים Kohanim didn't go first,
they were going first, correct? They were but they were at the
east side of the ירדן. Yarden. The פסוק pasuk says as soon
as they stepped in the ירדן Yarden the water stopped. So it
never says that they themselves crossed, went across the ירדן. Yarden. So
it's not that the כוהנים Kohanim were walking and as soon as
the bottom of their feet touched the water the water parted allowing
everybody else to... No, I mean you look at the פסוקים, psukim,
the פסוקים psukim actually sound like as soon as they stepped in
the water stopped. They wouldn't part? Exactly. Oh, I always understood, okay,
that the water was parting as they were walking. Yeah, I don't
think it says that in the פסוקים. psukim. The פסוקים psukim says
as soon as they stepped in. Okay, now, so he was... I
learned it as the water split and they went through like we
did... No, no, no, they stopped, they didn't split. The water stopped,
in the form of a wall, yes. Yeah, that's clear, yeah, that's
clear in the פסוק. pasuk. Because alright, it's alright, no, it was
not like ים סוף, Yam Suf, I assume that was mentioned yesterday
because as long as you stop it in one place then the
rest of it empties out, but then unlike ים סוף Yam Suf
you have the problem of the oncoming water, which is what the
גמרא Gemara dealt with. Alright, moving on. Okay, so he was smitten
there on the error even though it was just an error. רבי
יוחנן ורבי אלעזר, Rabbi Yochanan ve'Rabbi Elazar, חד אמר על עסקי שלו,
chad amar al iskei shalu, due to acts of error, it was
an error, nevertheless that was the consequence which is פשט pshat of
the פסוק. pasuk. וחד אמר שעשה צרכיו בפניו. Vechad amar she'asah tzorachav
befanav. So שלו shalu can mean to like, to fall off, to,
so it means he relieved himself in its presence. רש"י Rashi says
like נשל זיתך, nashal zeitecha, like to drop something. Anyway, so that's
obviously not פשט pshat in the פסוק, pasuk, but trying to maybe
make sense of why the consequences were so severe. וימת שם עם
ארון האלוקים, Vayamat sham im Aron Ha'elokim, he died there with the
ארון. Aron. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, now it's consistent with
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who acknowledged that it was an error and
he did not make him into a רשע. rasha. So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said עוזא בא לעולם הבא, Uza ba le'Olam Haba, עוזא,
Uza, okay, he suffered the consequences, but at the end of the
day it was an error. And therefore he goes into the world
to come, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, עם ארון האלוקים, im Aron Ha'elokim, with the
ארון Aron of God. מה ארון לעולם קיים, Mah Aron le'olam kayam,
the same as the ארון Aron will last forever, אף עוזא בא
לעולם הבא, af Uza ba le'Olam Haba, עוזא Uza will come into
the world to come. Okay. ויחר לדוד על אשר פרץ ה׳ פרץ
בעוזא, Vayichar le-David al asher paratz Hashem peretz b'Uzza, and דוד David
was fiery angry, right? It says ויחר אף ה׳ בעוזא, Vayichar af
Hashem b'Uzza, so parallel to God being fiery angry against עוזא, Uzza,
דוד David is fiery angry that God had done this thing. So
it doesn't say he was angry at God, but he was angry
about the fact that God had done this. אמר רב אלעזר Amar
Rav Elazar שנשתנו פניו כחררה. shenishtanu panav k'charara. The ויחר Vayichar means
his face blackened like a like a like a wafer that's, you
know, that's cooked over the coals. And the גמרא Gemara says, how
do you דרש darsh ויחר Vayichar that way? אלא מעתה כל היכא
דכתיב ויחר הכי נמי? Ela me'ata kol hacha de'chtiv vayichar hachi nami?
Anytime it says ויחר Vayichar you'll say that that's what it means?
I mean, ויחר Vayichar is a pretty common word in the תורה.
Torah. So how do you interpret it here as a special meaning?
So the גמרא Gemara says no. התם כתיב אף. Hatam ktiv af.
Normally when it says, it says ויחר אף, Vayichar af, which means
that the, literally by the way, it means the nostrils flared, like
it, like it burned, like, you know, smoke rose from the nostrils.
That's the image of ויחר אף. Vayichar af. But without the אף,
af, it's the word is strange. What got fiery? It was fiery
to him. Like you lose the whole image without the nose. Okay.
הכא לא כתיב אף. Hacha lo ktiv af. It doesn't say the
nose, the nostrils. So therefore we interpret it differently. All right. דרש
רבא מפני מה נענש דוד? Darash Rava mipnei ma ne'enash David? Why
was דוד David punished? מפני, Mipnei, meaning because it's funny, I mean
עוזא Uzza we understand was punished, but also this was, you know,
דוד, David, this was supposed to be like the, you know, the
highest day, like he was bringing the ארון aron and, you know,
and then this tragedy occurred. So to some degree דוד David was
deserving of it as well. What did דוד David do to be
deserving of it? מפני שקרא לדברי תורה זמירות, Mipnei she-kara l'divrei Torah
zmirot, because he in his own way did not give the necessary
weight and honor to the תורה. Torah. There's a parallel here. How
did he not give the weight of honor?
Well, he danced before the ארון.
aron. Well, that actually was true too, but that actually was seen
as proper honor interestingly, the
dancing. But it was that he called, I mean you're right, it
is connected to his dancing before it, but it's one thing to
dance before it as a way of showing joy, it's another thing
to refer to the תורה Torah itself as זמירות, zmirot, as like,
you know, tunes, as what would be the word for what's זמירות?
zmirot? Not hymns, songs, yes. You don't, you know, it's one thing
to rejoice by dancing, it's another thing to call it a song.
Okay. Of course says דברי השירה הזאת, divrei ha-shira ha-zot, but זמירות
zmirot has something, שירה shira is also weighty, שירה shira is like
poetry, you know, זמר zemer is like a common song. שנאמר זמירות
היו לי חוקיך, Shenemar zmirot hayu li chukecha, your edicts were to
me like זמירות, zmirot, בבית מגורי, b'veit megurai, in the place where
I was dwelling. Now, of course, what that also means is that
you enjoy the תורה, Torah, it's a source of joy, which is
similar to the dancing before it. But there's ways of expressing that
it's a source of joy, right, without calling them זמירות, zmirot, which
is actually recasting the very words themselves, you know. What? No, but
you see תהלים Tehillim are זמירות. zmirot. Yeah,
but the תהלים Tehillim are זמירות. zmirot. Not the חוקים. chukim. The
חוקים chukim are not זמירות. zmirot.
That's to get theologically negative. זמירות Zmirot
was problematic.
Yeah. Yeah, it's interesting. I know, because he also says תורה Torah
should be שעשוע, sha'ashua, you know, a plaything. But I think the
problem is that if you use a metaphor like you say, you
know, תורה Torah is like, you know, שעשוע, sha'ashua, it's a plaything,
right, so then clearly it's not reframing the very words, it's clearly
a metaphor. But calling them זמירות, zmirot, which is another genre of
writing, you know, it's like, oh, this is as good as reading
like a like a John le Carré novel, it's just so good.
You know, so it's like, so you know, calling it, how's it
different than calling it a plaything? That's a toy. No, one remains
a metaphor. The other is recasting it as a different genre of
writing, and that is seems to be what is sort of bothering
the גמרא. Gemara. And it's also looking for parallel, I think, to
the עוזא Uzza story. עוזא Uzza story. Okay. All right.
I'm surprised you didn't say Robert Ludlum.
Robert Ludlum, ugh, that's Robert Ludlum is awful. I would never say
that. Okay.
But
the last, the very last commandment in the תורה Torah is the
שירה.
shira. I said that, I mentioned שירה. shira. But שירה shira still
is like poetry. שירה Shira is elevated writing. זמירות Zmirot is very
much like just a song. Okay. So, okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר ליה הקדוש ברוך הוא. Amar leh ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu. God
says to him דברי תורה שכתוב בהם התעיף עיניך בו ואיננו. divrei
Torah she-katuv bahem hata'if einecha bo v'eineno. Just like, you know, flutter
your eye away from it and it'll disappear. It's so precious. You
have to, you know, be so careful with every word. And it's
so easy to lose. אתה קורא אותן זמירות? Ata kore otan zmirot?
You're calling them זמירות? zmirot? I don't really get the connection between
the fact that it's easy to lose תורה, Torah, you know, if
you don't pay constant attention to the idea of זמירות. zmirot. Like,
I like I don't know. I mean, there's other ways of describing
the weightiness of תורה. Torah. I'm not exactly sure about why this
is particularly relevant to the fact that they were called זמירות. zmirot.
Anyway, הריני מכשילך בדבר שאפילו תינוקות של בית רבן יודעין אותו. Hareini
machshilcha b'davar she-afilu tinokot shel beit raban yode'in oto. So maybe oh
maybe it's because of this next line. Because you don't treat them
weighty, you know, you don't pay sufficient care, it's just so fun
to learn תורה. Torah. You know, if it's always just fun and
it's never serious, then you won't then you're not paying sufficient care
to it. You're gonna suffer the consequence. This is why it says
התעיף עיניך בו he'ta'if eincha bo of not paying sufficient care. Why?
'Cause I'll make you make a mistake that even school children know
better, דכתיב ולבני קהת לא נתן כי עבודת הקדש עליהם בכתף ישאו.
dichshiv u'vnei Kehos lo nasan ki avodas hakodesh aleihem baksaf yisau. Right
in the פסוקים, psukim, it says the ארון aron had to be
carried by the shoulder. You don't put it on the wagon, right?
They didn't use any of the
wagons. ואתון עשיתון בעגלה, ve'atun asinu ba'agalah, and you put it on
a wagon. So you know, which is true, before the whole פרץ
עזא Perez Uzza the problem started, what are you doing carrying it
on a wagon? Doesn't he know, seriously? That's a good question. תינוקות
של בית רבן. tinokot shel beit raban. So it says it's a
consequence of having too much fun with the תורה. Torah. You know,
you gotta treat it seriously as well or you make these mistakes.
Okay. ויך באנשי בית שמש כי ראו בארון. vayach beanshei Beis Shemesh
ki rau ba'aron. Now because we're talking about the power of the
ארון, aron, we're sort of free associating here. So when the ארון
aron was on its way back, remember the time of עלי הכהן
Eli HaKohen when it was taken captive by the פלשתים Plishtim and
then they retrieved it. So it says that they—actually they
kind of sent it back.
They sent it back, yeah, 'cause it was, it wasn't doing any
good for them. So then it says it smote the people of
בית שמש Beis Shemesh because they saw the ארון. aron. They were
smitten. So they also like עזא Uzza were smitten, but they were
smitten just by looking at the ארון. aron. משום דראו ויך? mishum
de'rau vayach? Just because they looked at it they were smitten? So
I mean, well if you read, if you watched Raiders of the
Lost Ark, you would see. Anyway, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't buy
that. So רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, חד אמר
קוצרים ומשתחוים היו. chad amar kotzrim u'mishtachavim hayu. No, the problem was
that they were looking on, looking on while they were going about
their daily job. You know, they were harvesting in the field, there's
the ארון aron passing through and you're just continuing to harvest. Sort
of reminds you of the חסידיק Chassidic story about who
was it? The wagon driver who's changing his wheels and דאוונינג davening
מנחה Mincha at the same time and like the ליטוואק Litvak looked
at him and said, "Oh my God, I can't believe this wagon
driver, how dare he דאוון daven and at the same time his
hands are filled with grease, he's changing his wheels." And the חסיד
Chosid looks up to God and says like, "רבונו של עולם, Ribono
shel Olam, your people, even when their hands are filled with grease
they're still thinking about you." So
anyway, but I guess that didn't apply here.
They weren't דאוונינג, davening, they were just
looking on, they weren't stopping to do anything to pay
attention to what was going on.
It was ברדיטשוב? Berdichev? Okay. Anyway, וחד אמר מילי נמי אמרו. vechad
amar milai nami amar. It wasn't just that they were looking on
and they were impassive, or whatever you know they, without giving it
any weight. No, they actually said something to express this. So they
said the following: מאן אמריך דמראיית? man amricha de'mrayat? Like who had
got you so angry that you had to get angry at us?
Like, yeah what is this ארון? aron? It smote the פלשתים, Plishtim,
like you know who ever annoyed you that you were so annoying
to us? ומאן אסך דפויסת? u'man asach de'puyasat? And now what are
you, who appeased you? You know so they were like speaking to
it in a derogatory fashion, also personified fashion. Anyway, so they looked
at it dismissively or without giving it enough weight. ויך בעם שבעים
איש חמשים אלף איש. vayach ba'am shivim ish chamishim elef ish. And
smote among the people seventy, fifty thousand people. So that's a lot.
First of all, how many people were there in בית שמש?
Beis Shemesh? So רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba,
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, חד אמר שבעים איש היו. chad amar shivim
ish hayu. There were only, it was only seventy people that died.
וכל אחד ואחד שקול כחמשים אלף. vekol echad ve'echad shakula ki'chamishim elef.
But they were so important people that they were worth fifty thousand.
וחד אמר חמשים אלף היו. vechad amar chamishim elef hayu. No, there
were fifty thousand people that died. Sort of because the פסוק pasuk
divides the fifty thousand and the seven hundred. וכל אחד ואחד שקול
כשבעים סנהדרין. vekol echad ve'echad shakula kishivin Sanhedrin. And each one was
as big of a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham like the weightiness like
the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Okay. Back to דוד David transporting it. Yeah. Numbers
in the תורה.
Torah. Yes. I mean there are and also in the תלמוד, Talmud,
there's some huge numbers
of the sizes of the armies.
Yeah, I don't know, there are some ראשונים Rishonim or whatever that
do say by some of them that they're like a גוזמא, guzma,
that they're used as a, you know, just as a large number,
but you have to be careful with that, but yeah. Okay. ויהי
כי צעדו נשאי ארון ה' ששה צעדים. vayehi ki tza'adu nosei aron
Hashem shisha tze'adim. Now back to דוד David when they were carrying
the ארון. aron. When they would, those that were carrying the ארון
aron took the six steps. ויזבח שור ומריא. vayizbach shor u'meri. They
sacrificed an ox and a מריא. meri. What's a מריא? meri? A
fattened ox I think. What's a fattened cow? What do they count
to say a מריא meri is? Just a fattened ox and a
fatling. Fatling. What's a fatling? A fattened young animal like calf? Okay,
I don't know. Anyway, a מריא. meri. This is fattened. All right.
I guess you gotta know what a fatling is. Animal fattened for
slaughter. Clearly. Okay, clearly. Okay. Now, וכתיב uchsiv but another פסוק pasuk
in דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim when it repeats this says: שבעה פרים
ושבעה אילים. shiva parim veshiva eilim. It wasn't that one and one,
it wasn't but it was seven, seven oxen and seven rams. So
אמר רב פפא amar Rav Papa and also was rams instead of
a מריא. meri. אמר רב פפא בר שמואל, amar Rav Papa bar
Shmuel, על כל פסיעה ופסיעה. al kol p'sia up'sia. No, it says
six steps, but really for every step they took, they did a,
they did an ox and a fatling, על כל שש ושש פסיעות,
al kol sheish v'sheish p'si'ot, but every six steps they did שבעה
פרים ושבעה אילים. shivah parim v'shivah eilim. So that's a lot of
animals. So אמר ליה רב חסדא, Amar lei Rav Chisda, אי תימא
לית כל ארץ ישראל במות. ei teima leit kol Eretz Yisrael bamot.
You're, he didn't say where you're going to get all the animals,
but he said you're going to fill the entire land with במות
bamot every, every step they have to build a new במה. bamah.
But they were portable then. That I don't mean that's the problem.
The problem is is like you know like it doesn't, doesn't make
sense that they built a במה bamah every step. אלא אמר רב
חסדא, Ela amar Rav Chisda, על כל שש ושש פסיעות al kol
sheish v'sheish p'si'ot שור ומרי, shor u'm'ri, go with the simple sense
of the first פסוק, pasuk, every six steps they did a שור
ומרי, shor u'm'ri, which is still also a lot of במות. bamot.
על כל ששה סדרים של שש פסיעות, Al kol shishah sdarim shel
sheish p'si'ot, but in every set of six of the sixes, then
שבעה פרים ושבעה אילים. shivah parim v'shivah eilim. Okay, so that's how
we reconcile that. So these are presumably עולה olah offerings at each
step? Presumably, yeah. That's why and it's a lot of animals. כתיב
Ktiv כידון Kidon וכתיב u'chtiv נכון. Nachon. One verse refers to it
as כידון Kidon and one verse refers to it as נכון. Nachon.
Oh, so which is it, was it גורן כידון Goren Kidon or
גורן נכון Goren Nachon where this event of עוזא Uzza happened? אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, בתחילה כידון, bit'chilah Kidon, originally it was
כידון Kidon which is a word that means destruction, ולבסוף נכון, u'l'vasof
Nachon, but in the end it became proper. Why? Because since it
stayed there, you know, at the, you know, they left the ארון
Aron there at the בית אדום, Beit Edom, you know, it was
עובד אדום Oved Edom and then his house was blessed as a
result of it and so on, so in the end it brought
about blessing. רש"י Rashi has a different גירסא girsa which is or
he, רש"י Rashi quotes a מדרש Midrash that says that this place
of גורן כידון Goren Kidon was actually the same place of ארנן
היבוסי, Arnan ha-Yevusi, which was, you know, where they built the, sort
of מזבח mizbe'ach and turns out to be הר הבית. Har ha-Bayit.
So of course it's a little funny that that would have happened
at הר הבית Har ha-Bayit because then they mean that they'd already
brought the ארון Aron where they needed to have brought it. But
anyway, רש"י, Rashi, but, but then he says if that's true, he
suggests a different גירסא. girsa. Originally it was נכון, Nachon,
it was a place of sacrifice, ולבסוף כידון, u'l'vasof Kidon, but in
the end prophesying that the בית המקדש Beit ha-Mikdash would
be destroyed, which does not seem to be פשט pshat at all
of what's going on, but I just did want to share with
you רש"י Rashi brings the מדרש Midrash that, that combines the place
where the ארון Aron was, as גורן כידון, Goren Kidon, with the
ארנן היבוסי Arnan ha-Yevusi where the place where the מזבח mizbe'ach had
been. Yes, you had a question? I did. Did you just remind
us where was that link in the מדרש Midrash here that got
us to עוזא? Uzza? And in other words, how did we get
from because we were talking about the כהנים kohanim who carried the
ארון, Aron, the ארון Aron carried them across the ירדן, Yarden, so
about the power of the ארון. Aron. So since we were talking
about the power of the ארון Aron and that דוד David made
the mistake about, you know, with עוזא, Uzza, here the ארון Aron
was נושא את נושאיו, nosei et nos'av, etc. Okay. Anyway, moving on.
And the whole, this whole thing comes because of the משנה mishnah
mention of about the ברכות berachot and the קללות klalot that they
did when they crossed the ירדן. Yarden. So we're just discussing the
crossing of the ירדן. Yarden. So the ברכות berachot and the קללות
klalot which, which were נאמרים ne'emarim only בלשון הקודש. bi'lshon ha-kodesh. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara continues. נמצאת אתה אומר, Nimtzet atah omer, שלש
מיני אבנים, shlosh minei avanim, we're still in the story of crossing
the ירדן Yarden and the ברכה berachah whatever, but we're moving from
the ברכות berachot and the קללות. klalot. Actually this does tie into
the things that are נאמרים ne'emarim בכל לשון b'chol lashon because even
though the ברכות berachot and the קללות klalot were in Hebrew, the
תורה Torah was written באר היטב ba'er heiteiv when they crossed the
ירדן. Yarden. וכתבת על האבנים את כל דברי התורה הזאת באר היטב,
V'chatavta al ha-avanim et kol divrei ha-Torah ha-zot ba'er heiteiv, which is
understood to be שבעים לשון. shiv'im lashon. So there you get the
idea of many languages and ties back of course to that interesting,
you know, fast, curious line that you had a day or two
ago which was whether תורה Torah was, whether the תורה Torah was
נאמרת בכל לשון. ne'emeret b'chol lashon. What was the exact phrase of
the גמרא? Gemara? Whether it was כל התורה כולה בלשון הקודש נאמרה
או בכל לשון נאמרה. kol ha-Torah kullah bi'lshon ha-kodesh ne'emrah o b'chol
lashon ne'emrah. So does that mean that whether it was actually, you
know, given like at הר סיני Har Sinai בכל לשון? b'chol lashon?
Does it mean that it could be written, a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah can be written בכל לשון? b'chol lashon? I mean in the
end it seems like the most conventional interpretation is is that whether
it was presumed that any type of recitation, ritual recitation based on
the תורה, Torah, you know, could be בכל לשון, b'chol lashon, that
it's validated the, you know, interpretations of the תורה,
Torah,
even if it doesn't mean that the תורה Torah itself, we're not
talking about the object of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah or how
it was given at הר סיני, Har Sinai, but in terms of
its being sort of used ritually and validates interpretation, you know, many,
many, I shouldn't say interpretations, translations,
which does tie into the fact that, you know, it does create
a certain to this באר היטב ba'er heiteiv that they're doing when
they're crossing of the שבעים לשון, shiv'im lashon, that there's this idea
of, you know, which is quite different than the Catholic Church, you
know, or the, you know, or the Christian, you know, until whatever,
until Martin Luther, I mean but that wasn't Catholic yet, but anyway,
you know, there was only Latin and it was something to protect
the people from, you know, here it was something that you wanted
to give everybody access. Yes.
Did the חכמים Chachamim or ראשונים Rishonim think when, let's say if
it can be בכל לשון b'chol lashon it could be read in
the בית הכנסת Beit ha-Knesset let's say in Greek? Is the concept
that it would be written in Hebrew letters? No, no, תוספות *Tosfos*
deals with that. No, תוספות *Tosfos* says no, no, no, no, no.
תוספות *Tosfos* says you can't read it in a different language than
it's written because then you're not reading. Like it'll be like בעל
פה *ba'al peh*. Right, right, right. But the question is it's not
but but no, but תוספות *Tosfos* says but תוספות *Tosfos* tries to
move it away from the reading in the בית כנסת *Beis Knesset*.
He speaks about like the types of ritual recitations that we're dealing
with in this פרק *perek*. Is the basic presumption when the תורה
Torah *Torah* says say X, right, say, you know, you shall say
these words? Is the basic presumption of the תורה Torah *Torah* say
them in the original or is the basic presumption of the תורה
Torah *Torah* say them say them in any translation? So that's probably
the, you know, the best understanding of בכל לשון *bechol lashon* but
anyway it does again conceptually connect to בכל לשון *bechol lashon* but
the באר היטב be'er heitev. *be'er heiteiv*. Yes.
But putting this פרשת תורה Torah, *parshas Torah* or even all the
תורה *Torah* on stones, if they're outdoors they're eventually going to be
eroded.
Alright, so let's read a little about how good it was. Okay,
נמצאת אתה אומר שלושה מיני אבנים היו *Nimtzas atah omer shlosha minei
avanim hayu*. There were three sets of stones. אחד שהקים משה בארץ
מואב *Echad shehekim Moshe b'eretz Moav*. That you didn't know that happened.
משה *Moshe* put erected them in ארץ מואב *Eretz Moav* before they
crossed the ירדן *Yarden*. שנאמר *Shene'emar* בעבר הירדן בארץ מואב הואיל משה
באר את התורה הזאת *be'ever haYarden b'eretz Moav ho'il Moshe be'er es
haTorah hazos*. He began to explicate. ולהלן הוא אומר וכתבת עליהן את
כל דברי התורה הזאת באר היטב be'er heitev. *Ulehalan hu omer vechasavta
aleihen es kol divrei haTorah hazos be'er heiteiv*. So connects the באר
*be'er* at the beginning of דברים *Devarim* to the one at the
end, so if he explicated them, he did a similar way of
also creating a monument and writing them on the stones. ואף כאן
באר באר *Ve'af kan be'er be'er*. Okay. ואחד שהקים יהושע בתוך הירדן
*Ve'echad shehekim Yehoshua besoch haYarden*. And
one that was done
in the ירדן *Yarden*. שנאמר *Shene'emar* ושנים עשר אבנים הקים יהושע בתוך
הירדן *Ushteim esreh avanim hekim Yehoshua besoch haYarden*. Okay. ואחד שהקים בגלגל
*Ve'echad shehekim baGilgal*. And so he erected them in the ירדן *Yarden*
itself, but then he took them from there and he re-erected them
in גלגל *Gilgal*. שנאמר *Shene'emar* ואת שתים עשרה האבנים האלה אשר לקחו
*Ve'es shteim esreh ha'avanim ha'eleh asher lakchu* that they took from the
ירדן *Yarden* they erected in גלגל *Gilgal*. Okay. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*.
כיצד כתבו ישראל את התורה *Keitzad kasvu Yisrael es haTorah*? How did
they write it? Because also remember the תורה *Torah* says וסדת אותם
בסיד *vesadta osam basid*. Okay. You shall take these stones and you
shall plaster them with plaster. So we want to understand how that
works out, the stones and the plaster and so on. What?
I didn't believe back then משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu* had a whiteboard
you can't get...
Okay,
we'll keep that in mind because it's going to be an interesting
application. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*. על גבי אבנים
כתבוה *Al gabei avanim kesavuha*. They wrote it on the stones. שנאמר
וכתבת על האבנים את כל דברי התורה הזאת *Shene'emar vechasavta al ha'avanim
es kol divrei haTorah hazos* ואחר כך סדו אותן בסיד *Ve'achar kach
sadu osan basid*. And then after they wrote on the stones they
covered it up with plaster. So presumably it means they carved it
into the stones, you know, otherwise nobody would be able to see
it at all.
But nevertheless, you know, even if it's carved into the stones, if
it was covered with plaster it's probably a little bit less readable,
which is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is about to ask. אמר
לו רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Amar lo Rabbi Shimon*. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* who we're going to see has a different interpretation
about how they wrote it on the stones, said to him לדבריך
היאך למדו אומות שבאותו הזמן תורה *Lidvarecha heich lamdu umos shebe'oso hazman
Torah*? How did the nations of that time learn תורה *Torah*? The
whole purpose was it's very fascinating, right? It's not, you know, it's
like taking for granted that the whole purpose of writing this באר
היטב be'er heitev *be'er heiteiv* and then the שבעים לשון shivim lashon
*shivim lashon* is that you want, you know, if you're going into
the land and creating, you know, a land of God's, you know,
law and God's תורה *Torah* and built on that, it's not that
you want to sort of, you know, hoard that. You want that
to be a model. And therefore you want to be teaching. I
mean it's very powerful if you think about that the going into
the land, the באר היטב *be'er heiteiv*, right? I mean just think
about that for a minute. The פשט pshat? *pshat* of the פסוקים
*pesukim* is like this is like the covenant, right? The ערבות מואב
*Arvos Moav* is the covenant. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* spoke about the
תנאי *tnai* that יהושע *Yehoshua* made in the middle of the ירדן
*Yarden*. You do the אלות *alos*, you're about to enter into the
land, the אלות *alos* and the הקללות והברכות *haklalos vehabrachos*. Like this
is the consequence, you're in this land for the purpose or based
on this, you know, you know, the תורה *Torah* and keeping the
laws of the תורה *Torah* etc. And that's באר היטב *be'er heiteiv*.
פשט *pshat* of the פסוק *pasuk* is you should all know what
this תורה *Torah* is. And now we're completely reversing the focus. You're
going into the land and you have to use your presence in
the land as a way that all the nations should learn תורה
*Torah*, right? That's it's really radically different than the than the פשט
*pshat* of the פסוקים *pesukim* as opposed to like keeping the תורה
*Torah* as ours. So anyway, so his challenge was if it's covered
up with plaster, how did they learn it? So we'll see in
a minute what he says. אמר לו בינה יתירה נתן בהם הקדוש
ברוך הוא *Amar lo binah yeseirah nasan bahem HaKadosh Baruch Hu*. God
gave them particular insight, wisdom, understanding. ושיגרו נוטירין שלהם *Veshigru notirin shelahem*.
And they sent their scribes. וקילפו את הסיד *Vekilpu es hasid*. And
they peeled off the plaster והשיאוה *Vehasi'uha*. And they carried it with
them. So you're talking about a whiteboard, this is one of those
things, those smartboards, you push a button and everything you write, right,
it goes behind the wall and somehow it takes a picture of
it. So this is like a carbon copy. That's why they plastered
it because then they pulled off the plaster and then actually it
was the mirror image of it, but actually it's really good because
then you can use this to print. Right? If you think about
it, you've got now a perfect, right, you've got that's exactly how
it works.
It's רבא די- *Raba di-* silk screen תורה *Torah*.
But no, but think think about how perfect it is. When you
carve in, so the plaster sort of is risen, which is exactly
the way type works. Like it's risen so that it can then
be used. Create an impression on the thing. So that's what they
did. This was perfect. This was the way of publishing the תורה
for all the nations. Exactly. Okay. ועל דבר זה נחתם גזר דינם
לבאר שחת.
Ve'al davar zeh nechtam gzar
dinam l've'er shachat.
Ah,
but ultimately that sealed their, you know, them into the eternal damnation
or whatever. שהיה להם ללמוד ולא למדו. Shehaya lahem lilmod velo lamdu.
It was so easy, they could have had the תורה in שבעים
לשון shivim lashon, and they had, you know, a printing press, an
early printing press, and they didn't learn it. So that, that sealed
their, their judgment.
By the way, באר שחת be'er shachat and באר היטב.
Oh,
I didn't think about that. That's good. באר שחת be'er shachat and
באר היטב. That's good. שכח. shkoach. Okay. Okay. רבי שמעון אומר. Rabbi
Shimon omer. Now רבי שמעון who challenged this, which now seems like
a brilliant interpretation, said, על גבי סיד כתבוה. al gabei sid ktavuha.
He wrote, they wrote it on top of the plaster. וכתב להם
למטה, vechatav lahem lemata, and he wrote underneath, למען אשר לא ילמדו
אתכם לעשות ככל התועבות. leman asher lo yilamdu etchem la'asot kechol hato'evot.
That God is bringing in that you have to wipe out the
שבעים אומות shivim umot so that they shouldn't teach you, you shouldn't
learn from their deeds. And what that's going to translate into is
as a sort of as an object lesson to the other nations
that they should learn. They never took this and they took the
תורה and they learned that the שבעים אומות... shivim umot...
What's going on? Like this for, for... Okay.
There's obviously some, some... Anyway, the שבעים אומות shivim umot took this
and the message wasn't just learn it as abstract knowledge. I mean,
that wasn't the message for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda as well. Right?
The message for him was you had to, you should have learned
it and followed it. But here, there was also a clear message.
This is why they die. This is why it wipes them out.
You know, you guys better learn. You know, now of course we
didn't have a מצוה mitzvah to do that outside of ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. But nevertheless, there was sort of like that message. Apparently,
according to him, this was his challenge before he realized, before רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda: answered back that they should be used as a
type of, of a, of a, of a printing press, he assumes
no, they did pull off the plaster. But that's why it has
to be written on top of the plaster, not under the plaster.
So he had it on top of the plaster and apparently they
pulled off the plaster and they sent it to the non-Jews. Either
way, they're answering Charlie's question, which is if it's שבעים לשון, shivim
lashon what good does שבעים לשון do if it's standing in ארץ
ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Right? If באר היטב means for, for the Israelites,
okay, there's the place where the תורה is written. You can go
pilgrimage to that site and see it and so on. But if
it's for the אומות העולם, umot ha'olam, what good does it do?
So one explanation was this type of a plaster that became a
printing press. And the other explanation was they wrote it on top
of the plaster and they pulled off the plaster and they sent
the plaster to the, to the other nations. Okay. אמר
רבא בר שילא, Amar Rava bar Shila, where was it? מאי טעמא
דרבי שמעון? Mai ta'ama deRabbi Shimon? What's his reason? דכתיב... dechtiv... I'm
sorry, I skipped a line. למען אשר לא ילמדו אתכם לעשות ככל.
leman asher lo yilamdu etchem la'asot kechol. הא למדת שאם היו חוזרים
בתשובה, ha lamadeta she'im hayu chozrim bitshuva, if they would have repented,
היו מקבלין אותן. hayu mekabelin otan. They would have been accepted them.
Which means the way the גמרא Gemara is going to understand this
is that even the שבעים אומות shivim umot outside of ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, if they would change their ways, if we ever go
to war against them, like we do a מלחמת רשות milchemet reshut
outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Here's the question: do we have
a מצוה mitzvah to destroy the שבעים אומות shivim umot in a
war that we might happen to fight outside of ארץ ישראל? Eretz
Yisrael? So he said no, if they have mended their ways. Okay.
Now היו מקבלין אותן, hayu mekabelin otan, does that mean we would
accept them, they could actually convert? Is this Tali's simplest פשט? But
for also one thing it just means is, is what do you
call it? Is that we would not have to wipe them out.
רש"י Rashi says we would even accept them if they would convert.
Okay. אמר רבא בר שילא, Amar Rava bar Shila, מאי טעמא דרבי
שמעון? mai ta'ama deRabbi Shimon? What's his reason? דכתיב, dechtiv, והיו עמים
משרפות שיד, vehayu amim misrephot sid, the nations will be, you know,
like the, the burning of the, the fire pits of the, of
plaster. על עסקי סיד, al iskei sid, because of the plaster. They
should have learned from the plaster and if not, that's why they
are going to burn in גיהנום. Gehenom. רבי יהודה: Rabbi Yehuda כסיד,
kasid, no, just like plaster. מה סיד אין לו תקנה אלא שרפה
אף אותם עובדי כוכבים אין להם תקנה אלא שרפה. mah sid ein
lo takana ela sreifa af otam ovdei kochavim ein lahem takana ela
sreifa. So remember, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said this was, this sealed
their fate. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, seems to feel, the way
the גמרא is reading it, or actually this might be a quote
of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda that maybe even it's hard to understand
that like, um, that אין להם תקנה, ein lahem takana, right, seems
to be referring to, meaning it's funny. On the one hand the
general non-Jews got it so that they should learn from it. So
you're not going to say אין להם תקנה ein lahem takana for
the general non-Jews, then what was the point? So it seems that
the גמרא is now creating this or there is this debate in
terms of the שבעה עממין shiva amamin that live outside of ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay? That one, that רבי שמעון says על עסקי
סיד, al iskei sid, if the שבעה עממין shiva amamin had learned
from the תורה, they would not have been wiped out. And רבי
יהודה says no, the שבעה עממין shiva amamin had no choice, had
no chance. They were going to be destroyed without any, they אין
להם תקנה. ein lahem takana. Okay. Yes. What? Of the כותים? Kutim?
אומות העולם? umot ha'olam?
Oh,
yeah, so כותים, Kutim, right, because כותים, Kutim, Samaritans, don't belong here,
clearly. I should have stopped and said that כותים, Kutim, Samaritans, don't
belong here, clearly. It's talking about, it's a what do you call
it, it's a censored word. But still, the question still is... Okay,
we'd better end. I'm gonna get way distracted. Anyway, the sentence still
is,
the simple sense of אומות העולם Umos Haolam would still be the
non-Jews in general. Okay, but the אין להם תקנה, ein lahem takanah,
oh, I can't do this. Okay, so we'll pick up with this
idea tomorrow.